A Guide to the Lottie Louise Hines papers, 1849-1948
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lottie Louise Hines papers, 1849-1948
The Library of Virginia
53442
4 cubic feet (6 boxes and 2 scrapbooks)
Lottie Louise Hines
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Lottie Louise Hines Trust and Colonel John Banister Chapter (NSDAR), Petersburg, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Lottie Louise Williamson was born in Nottoway County, Virginia, to Albert Williamson (1825-1892) and Mary Frances Watts Williamson (1842-1895). She married William Washington Hines (1869-1942), a merchant in in the oil business, in Washington D.C. on 14 May 1896, and they had one daughter. The Hines lived in Petersburg, Virginia, and Lottie Louise Hines became active in the community. She was the founding regent of the Colonel John Banister Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution. Hines was a member of the Petersburg chapter of the Equal Suffrage League and served as president of the Women's Democratic Club of Petersburg. She was one of seven women delegates out of 30 delegates to the 1933 Virginia convention to repeal the 18th amendment (Prohibition). Hines was the first director of the Petersburg Community Gardens, and served as president of the Virginia Cancer Foundation. Lottie Louise Williamson Hines died 14 April 1940 in Petersburg and was buried in Blandford Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1849-1948, of Lottie Louise Williamson Hines (1875-1940) of Petersburg, Virginia, consisting of applications, articles, correspondence, genealogical charts and notes, postcards, scrapbooks, and other papers documenting Hines' family research for membership in genealogical societies; as well as papers concerning the Colonel John Banister Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Lottie Louise Hines papers
Series II: Colonel John Banister Chapers (DAR) papers
Contents List
- Series I: Lottie Louise Hines papers., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Lottie Louise Hines papers contain correspondence with Blanche Adams Chapman (1895-1954); Minnie G. Cook (1964-1957); T. S. Williamson (1865-1945) and others regarding genealogical research; applications for membership in genealogical organizations; genealogical notes and charts on the Allen, Coker, Green, Hines, Traylor, Watts, Williamson, and Wood families; and genealogical information and papers concerning Anne Louise Hines (1897-1924). Also includes papers regarding Camp Lee (Prince George County, Virginia) and World War I; as well as articles on life after death, evolution and religion, and other topics.
  - Blanche Adams Chapman correspondence, 1938, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minnie G. Cook correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - T. S. Williamson correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and papers (bound together in notebook), 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence and papers (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Society Daughters of the American Colonists--family lines for membership application (Allen, Bennett, Clay, Filmer, Hobbs, and Williamson families) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Society Daughters of Founders and Patriots of America--membership (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Daughters of the Barons of Runnemeade; Order of the First Families of Virginia; Society Americans of Royal Descent--papers (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Genealogical records for Anne Louise Hines (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family genealogical information--Allen and Williamson (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family genealogical information--Coker, Green, and Williamson (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Family genealogical information--Hines and Williamson (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Family genealogical information--Traylor, Watts, Williamson, and Wood (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family genealogical information--Williamson (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Bayonet: Remembrance Book of Camp Lee, to Anne Louise Hines from Cal, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous papers relating to Camp Lee and World War I, 1917-1921, no date (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Evolution and Religion by Harry Emerson Fosdick, Ladies' Home Journal, September 1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Seven Minutes in Eternity: The Amazing Experience that Made Me Over by William Dudley Pelley, The American Magazine, March 1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Beyond the Grave: How Fares It With the Happy Dead and The Life to Come by Clarence Edward McCartney (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes on Elemental (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Empty envelopes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Anne Louise Hines scrapbook, 1897-1932 (separate volume)
- Series II: Colonel John Banister Chapter (DAR) papers., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 2-3)
  Colonel John Banister Chapter (DAR) papers contain correspondence regarding the chapter; financial statement for 1947-1948; genealogical research regarding members; historical research on Petersburg, Virginia, and surrounding counties; correspondence with and plaque from the United States Constitution Sesquicentennial Commission, 1937-1939; letters, 1849, of Harriet Mertens Johnson (1815-1852) of Petersburg to her brother and sister; and books.
  - Chapter papers, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chapter papers, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chapter papers, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial report, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Colonial Homes Below the Falls of the Appomattox by Fannie Dunn, typescript copy of article published in Petersburg Daily Index Appeal, 14 January 1900 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Colonial Virginia Marriage Laws and Some Early Henrico County Marriages by Minnie G. Cook (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Items Concerning Historic Mecklenburg County, Virginia (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Family genealogical information--Barret and Bolling (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - William Harris and Elizabeth Harris Archer by Minnie G. Cook (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Family genealogical information--Montgomery (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Harriet Mertens Johnson letters, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - National Society, Daughters of the American Revolution and Smithsonian Institute postcards (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - United States Constitution Sesquicentennial Commission plaque, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - United States Constitution Sesquicentennial Commission papers, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Children of the American Revolution--magazine, song sheets, and pamphlet, 1938, no date (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1939, no date (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Heavner-Hefner-Hevener of the Virginias, Volume I--Jacob, Volume II--Frederick, by Dennis N. Hevener, Jr. (Box 3)
  - 1815 Directory of Virginia Landowners (and Gazetteer), Volume Five: Southwest Region abstracted by Roger G. Ward (Box 3)
  - Orange County Land Patents, second edition, by Ulysses P. Joyner, Jr. (Box 3)
  - Surry County, Virginia, Court Orders, 1741-1751: An Every-Name Index by T.L.C. Genealogy (Box 3)
  - Virginia Land Office Inventory by the Virginia State Library (Box 3)
  - The North Carolina Genealogical Society Journal, volume XIX, no. 2, May 1993 (Box 3)
  - Clark County Kentucky Marriage 1793-1850: Alphabetical by Groom (Box 3)
  - Kentucky Bluegrass Roots, volume fourteen, number 3, Fall, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution scrapbook, 1964-1965 (separate volume)